Holley Manufacturing Company Records
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Holley Manufacturing Company Records.
undated, 1847-1933.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Rudd, Charles E.
75 linear feet.
The Holley Manufacturing Company of Lakeville (Salisbury), Connecticut, produced pocket cutlery and related products, from 1844 until 1946. Holley Manufacturing Company's sales and production declined after 1933 and the firm was dissolved in 1946.
MSS19800028
History
The Holley Manufacturing Company of Lakeville (Salisbury), Connecticut, produced pocket cutlery and related products, from 1844 until 1946. Founded in 1844 by Alexander Hamilton Holley and George Merwin as Holley and Merwin, the Company claimed to be the oldest manufacturer of pocket cutlery in the United States. The company name was later changed to Holley & Company. In 1854, it was incorporated as the Holley Manufacturing Company, with Alexander H. Holley as president, George B. Burrall, treasurer, and William B. Rudd, secretary. William Rudd's son, Malcolm D. Rudd, succeeded him as treasurer and general manager, serving in that position until 1942. Its customers were retailers and small jobbers, mostly in New England, Pennsylvania, and upper New York State. Total annual sales of the company probably did not exceed $50,000 from 1844 to 1925, or $10,000 from 1925 to 1933. Holley Manufacturing Company's sales and production declined after 1933 and the firm was dissolved in 1946.
Scope and Content
The Holley Manufacturing Company records provide detailed information about this important pocket cutlery firm. The bulk of this collection consists of correspondence with customers, hardware dealers, other manufacturing companies, sales agents, the Manufacturers Association of Connecticut, and credit and collecting agencies. The records also include substantial information about employees, sales, and production, and finances.
Arrangement
Series I: Correspondence ( undated, 1854-1933 ) consists of incoming correspondence (1854-1933), letters from the agents (1887-1933), select correspondence from R.G. Dun Company, hardware dealers, the Manufacturers Association of Connecticut, and the firm of Kemble and Mills; and outgoing correspondence (1847-1933).
Series II: Administrative Records ( undated, 1852-1920 ) contains contracts, legal and semi-legal documents, insurance policies, patents, personnel policies, reports, tax records, blueprints, and notebooks.
Series III: General Accounts ( undated, 1847-1928 ) consists of daybooks, journals, ledgers, accounting statements, and other general account records.
Series IV: Labor Records ( undated, 1854-1920 ) consists of records related to payroll and employee's accounts.
Series V: Production Records ( undated, 1853-1927 ) consists of inventory books, cost estimates, records of raw material used, and material samples.
Series VI: Sales Records ( undated, 1850-1938 ) consists of catalog and price lists (1850-1934), salesmen's reports and trip books (1853-1869), customer credit ratings (1856-1858), customer lists (1904-1920), Boyd's City Dispatch Credit reports (1911-1932), R.G. Dun and Company reports (1869-1876), sales summaries (1901-1914), photographs of Holley pocket knives, and price lists and catalogs from other cutlery and silver manufacturing companies.
Series VII: Griggs & Chapin Company ( undated, 1882-1887 ) contains business records of Griggs & Chapin Company, a general store evidently used by the Holley Company to pay employees in kind.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of Connecticut business records. See also the papers of Malcolm D. Rudd. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Holley, Alexander H. (Alexander Hamilton), 1804-1887.; Burrall, George B.; Rudd, Malcolm Day, b. 1877.; Rudd, William B. (William Beardslee)
Organizations:
American Pocket Cutlery Manufacturers Association.
Subjects:
Cutlery trade--Connecticut.; Industrial relations--Connecticut.; Labor unions--Connecticut.; Trade and professional associations--Connecticut.; Trade-union meetings--Connecticut.; Silver-plated flatware--United States.; Manufactures--Connecticut.; Collection agencies--Connecticut.; Hardware stores--Connecticut.; Connecticut--Business, industries, and trades--Cutlery.; Lakeville (Conn.--Business, industries, and trades--Cutlery.; Torrington (Conn.)--Business, industries, and trades--Cutlery.
Document Types:
Insurance Policies.; Catalogs.; Inventories.; Correspondence.; Administrative Records.; Financial Records.; General Accounts.; Labor Records.; Production Records.; Sales Records.
Occupations:
Cutlery manufacturer.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated by Yale University Libraries in 1979.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Correspondence, undated, 1854-1933
  - Incoming Correspondence
    - 1854 May - 1867 September (Box 1)
    - 1867 October - 1869 August (Box 2)
    - 1869 September - 1871 February (Box 3)
    - 1871 March - 1872 June (Box 4)
    - 1872 July - 1873 December (Box 5)
    - 1874 January - 1875 August (Box 6)
    - 1975 September - 1877 August (Box 7)
    - 1877 September - 1879 December (Box 8)
    - 1880 January - 1881 December (Box 9)
    - 1882 January - 1883 October (Box 10)
    - 1883 November - 1885 June (Box 11)
    - 1885 July - 1887 April (Box 12)
    - 1887 May - 1890 February (Box 13)
    - 1890 March - 1891 December (Box 14)
    - 1892 January - 1893 September (Box 15)
    - 1895 October - 1897 December (Box 16)
    - 1898 January - 1899 August (Box 17)
    - 1898 January - 1899 August (Box 18)
    - 1899 August - 1901 April (Box 19)
    - 1901 April - 1902 March (Box 20)
    - 1902 March - 1903 January (Box 21)
    - 1903 January - 1903 November (Box 22)
    - 1903 December - 1904 October (Box 23)
    - 1904 November - 1905 October (Box 24)
    - 1905 November - 1906 October (Box 25)
    - 1906 October - 1907 August (Box 26)
    - 1907 September - 1908 October (Box 27)
    - 1908 October - 1909 September (Box 28)
    - 1909 September - 1910 May (Box 29)
    - 1910 June - 1911 April (Box 30)
    - 1911 May - 1912 April (Box 31)
    - 1912 April - 1913 November (Box 32)
    - 1913 December - 1915 March (Box 33)
    - 1915 April - 1917 February (Box 34)
    - 1917 February - 1918 November (Box 35)
    - 1918 December - 1920 June (Box 36)
    - 1920 July - 1923 March (Box 37)
    - 1923 April - 1933 (Box 38)
  - Letters from agents
    - 1887-1896 (Box 39)
    - 1896-1904 (Box 40)
    - 1905-1908 (Box 41)
    - 1908 September - 1913 April (Box 42)
    - 1913 April - 1933 (Box 43)
  - Select Correspondence
    - R.G. Dun & Co., undated (Box 43)
    - Hardware Dealers, undated
    - Manufacturers and Association of Connecticut, undated
    - Kemble & Mills, undated
  - Outgoing Correspondence
    - 1847 November - 1901 October (Box 44)
    - 1901 October - 1905 November (Box 45)
    - 1905 November - 1910 September (Box 46)
    - 1910 September - 1915 January (Box 47)
    - 1915 January - 1933 (Box 48)
    - Telegrams, 1911-1917
    - Loose Letters, 1884-1933
- Series II: Administrative Records, undated, 1852-1920
  - Contracts, 1851-1863 (Box 49)
  - Contracts, 1891-1912
  - Contracts and Agreements, 1852-1899
  - Insurance policies, undated
  - Legal papers, 1851-1914
  - Notebooks: Union Hall Meetings; Holley Co. Band; Malcolm D. Rudd; District no. 4, undated, 1901
  - Patents: other companies, 1868-1905
  - Personnel: State of Connecticut publications on labor laws and workmen's compensation, 1913-1919
  - Personnel policies and benefits, 1851, 1910-1912
  - Reports and production procedures, 1893-1914
  - Silver Plated Ware Manufacturers Association, 1880
  - Taxes and census of manufactures, 1851-1870
  - Taxable list of property, 1903-1932 (Othertype OS)
  - Holley Block: blueprints, undated (Othertype OS)
  - Equipment: blueprints and drawings, undated, 1911 (Othertype OS)
  - Iron Age Bulletin, 1875, 1887 (Othertype OS)
- Series III: General Account Records, undated, 1847-1928
  - Daybooks
    - 1850 March - 1857 August (Box 50)
    - 1854 June - 1882 February (Box 51)
  - Journals
    - 1901 January - 1910 January (Box 52)
    - 1910 January - 1927 December (Box 53)
  - Ledgers
    - 1846-1877 (Box 54)
    - 1875-1891 (Box 55)
    - 1892-1912 (Box 56)
    - 1912-1927 (Box 57)
  - Particular expenses ledger, 1901-1928 (Box 58)
  - Accounting statements, 1901-1930 (Box 59)
  - Lists of draft issued, 1888-1922
  - Collection sheets, undated, 1865-1878
  - Accounts payable and receivable ledger, 1847-1858
  - Account book, 1860-1867
  - Closed accounts for collection by Kemble & Mills, 1908-1909
  - Account statements and bills, 1855-1907, 1929 (Othertype OS)
- Series IV: Labor Records, undated, 1854-1920
  - Work Book Ledgers
    - 1854 May - 1873 November (Box 60)
    - 1873 December - 1895 November (Box 61)
    - 1895 November - 1920 December (Box 62)
  - Workmen's Ledgers (payroll and expenses)
    - 1854 June - 1890 July (Box 63)
    - 1890 July - 1911 July (Box 64)
  - Time books, 1866-1928 (Box 65)
  - Wage Journals for individuals, 1873-1920
  - Employees record book, 1900-1912
- Series V: Production Records, undated, 1853-1927
  - Inventory books, rough copies, 1875, 1887-1920 (Box 66)
  - Inventory books, smooth copies, 1853-1895 (Box 67)
  - Inventory books, smooth copies, 1896-1927 (Box 68)
  - Inventory books of knives, 1862-1873
  - Inventory, schedule and notes, 1858-1912 (Box 69)
  - Comparative production costs, 1865-1879
  - Cost estimates, 1899-1924
  - Cost estimates books, 1855-1879, 1901-1914
  - Raw material used, 1904-1922
  - Ledger of metals, gauges, and patterns, 1903
  - Reference book, C.E. Rudd, 1906
  - Gasoline engine time book, 1907
  - Finishing room: activity price book, 1910-1914
  - Production record books
  - Material Samples, undated (Box 70)
    - White Heat Products Co.
    - Shults Co.
    - Bird Glue Co.
    - Eagle Lock Co.
    - R. Wallace & Sons Manufacturing Co.
    - Janell Belting Co.
    - Delaware Hard Fiber Co.
    - Arlington Co.
    - Hammacher, Schlemmer and Co.
    - Diamond Co. (Box 71)
    - Angiers Co.
    - Krallert Co.
    - Hammer Co.
    - Harlem Valley's Firemen's Association
    - DeHaven Manufacturing Co.
    - F.W. Devoe & C.T. Reynolds Co.
    - Salisbury, Hooley Co.
    - Celluloid Co.
    - Washington Emery Mills Co.
    - American Vulcanized Fiber Co.
    - Broken Shield Co.
    - Jos. Stelwagon Co.
    - Shercliffe & Sons (Box 72)
    - Uncon Pearl Works
    - Applebee & Newman
    - R.S. Peck & Co.
    - Miscellaneous
    - Objects (Box 73)
- Series VI: Sales Records, undated, 1850-1938
  - Advertisements and business cards, undated (Box 74)
  - Photographs of Holley pocket knives, undated, 1876
  - Catalog, 1896
  - Customer credit rating book, 1856-1858
  - Price lists, 1850-1934
  - Sales agents' trip books, 1853-1869
  - Sales agents' expense and collection reports, 1880-1917 (Box 75)
  - Sales agents' notebooks, undated, 1887
  - Sales agents' expense books, 1901-1902
  - Sales agents' commission accounts, 1905-1917
  - American Table Cutlery Manufacturers Association, 1879-1881
  - Lamson & Goodnow Manufacturing Co.: Price lists, 1869-1894
  - Meriden Cutlery Co.: Price list and catalog, 1870-1878
  - Rogers Cutlery Co. and William Roger Manufacturing Co.: price list and catalogs, 1877-1884
  - Wallace Brothers: price lists, 1878-1881
  - Price lists and advertisements: other companies, 1870-1893
  - Dun's reports, 1868-1876
  - Boyd's City Dispatch, 1911-1932
  - R.G. Dun and Co., Reference Book, 1917 (Box 76)
  - Printed price lists and advertisements, undated (Othertype OS)
  - R.G. Dun and Co. printed maps, 1909
- Series VII: Griggs & Chapin Company, 1882-1887
  - Daybook, 1882-1883 (Box 77)
  - General Ledger, 1883-1884
  - Correspondence, bills, receipts, 1883-1887 (Box 78)